hi guys and welcome back to Kats
lacrosse stick in today's video I'm
going to be doing a beginner's going to
have to start off cross stitching some
people think it's really easy and
straightforward but if you're a complete
beginner it can be a bit overwhelming so
in this video I will show you really
easily step-by-step with clear
instructions how exactly to start your
first ever cross stitch project if
you're new to Katz for the cross stitch
then welcome I'm Sally I am the owner
and designer of the business I would
absolutely love you to click subscribe
below and join this community
I have no new videos regularly all about
cross stitch time lapses blogs tutorials
tips information all sorts of things
cross stitch really so please do click
the button and join us and if you have
enjoyed this video then please give it a
thumbs up below so I know to make more
like this for you so to start off then
we've got hair just a selection of the
main things that you're going to need to
get cross stitching of course you're
going to have your pattern also but
these are the main supplies so we've got
scissors these are fish scars orange
scissors which I find the best to use or
the sharpest some DMC thread some DMC
gold-plated needles two different types
of fabric these are both spy got fabrics
which I find the best brand to use and
some embroidery hoops so to start off
with then this fabric here is his
beautiful blush pale pink is on a six
inch hoop and this is a 25 count lagana
even weave fabric the color is 405 by
Zweig art if anyone's interested and the
next fabric that I'm going to show you
how to cross stitch on is going to be
this beautiful cream serve I got 14
count Eider and that's in a 7 inch hoop
a link absolutely everything down below
in the description box you can find it
really easily there are three different
ways to start off cross stitching so I'm
going to go through them today
step-by-step so that you can see exactly
what's involved and choose which one is
best for you the first one then we're
going to be stitching on the cream 14
count aider and this is DMC thread color
eight one six which is this really rich
dark red color we're going to be
stitching with a sigh
twenty-four needle this is by DMC and
it's nickel-plated steel but the eye is
18 karat gold-plated which makes it much
easier to thread your cotton through or
your floss if you're in America and also
it helps that thread glide easily
through the eye of the needle during
stitching will also be using this
pumpkiny reminder I'll link everything
down below if you are interested in
having a look at our range of magnetic
needle minders - there's also a separate
video that goes through exactly what is
a needle winder if you've never used one
before so the DMC cotton comes in six
strands but we'll only be using two
strands to stitch on 14 count ADA the
way I separate them and there are lots
of different methods is just to use my
finger to really gently peel them apart
as opposed to pulling the threads out
which sometimes can get a little bit
knotted next you need to thread your
needle through the eye I find it a bit
easier actually if you almost put the
needle over the thread as opposed trying
to push the threads through the eye of a
needle the length of this piece of
thread is about the same distance from
my hand to my elbow which I just find a
really nice easy workable length of
thread to use while stitching anything
longer and it might get knotted anything
shorter and you're going to run out of
the cotton much quicker to start off
them with the most simplest way of
starting to cross stitch we're going to
leave a tail of about 5 - 10 centimetres
push the needle from the back of your
fabric to the front in any of the holes
and you're going to go down again from
the bottom left over into the top right
hand corner come back up through the top
left hand corner and back down through
the bottom right hand corner it doesn't
really matter which way around you do it
in terms of left or right as long as you
stay consistent throughout all of your
different stitches
with this way of starting which just has
this loose end which is a simplest we're
going to try to catch the back thread so
when you do your next few stitches try
on the back to loop it over ever so
slightly detail on the back side and
secure that down
using the next few stitches as you can
see here keep stitching according to the
pattern bottom left to top right top
left down to bottom right and when
you're done you can leave your needle
secure on to the magnetic needle minder
once you're finished with that thread or
that piece of stitching in that color
you're going to need to finish off the
end so go round the back and simply push
it through a couple of stitches to
secure and trim off the end the next way
of starting to cross stitch is we're
going to knot the end of the thread this
isn't one that I would necessarily
recommend but I know lots of stitches
use it and find it really simple and
it's their preferred method
so simply knot the ends of the thread
again you're using two strands a
smallish not as small as you can get
away with really and we're starting
again so pushing it from the back of the
fabric to the front first of all in the
bottom left hand corner of one of these
squares on the grid and down through the
top right hand corner here you can see
that I'm doing what are called half
stitches so really it's just half of a
cross it's just one diagonal stitch so
sometimes a pattern might call for half
stitches in particular caterpillar cross
stitch patterns tend to only use whole
stitches because it's the easiest but
sometimes just check on the pattern you
will see a symbol that looks instead of
an X more like this type of a stitch or
even if the pattern calls for full
stitches you might want to do a larger
section in half stitches particularly if
you're going horizontally in a row or
vertically in a column and then go back
over them in the same direction to
finish off the final cross stitch but
just again make sure that they're all
consistent in terms of which angle
you're coming down across for the top
half stitch if that makes sense so you
can see here they're all pointing to the
right and when I'm coming back over to
them back over them and when I'm coming
back over them to make the final cross
and they are all pointing to the
left-hand side coming down in the top
left hand corner to finish off again
once you've completed that section of
stitching same method just simply push
the needle through really
they I would say at least two of the
stitches on the back pull it through
that secures it nicely and then trim it
off pretty much as close as you can get
away with to the stitches because that
way you're not having a long tail
hanging around on the back which might
then get caught when you're doing some
more stitches using a different color
thread next the next way we're going to
learn to start off cross stitching is
using the loop method this time we only
need one of the six strands of thread so
again I'm just running my finger down
here really slowly and carefully to
separate out the strands but this time
I'm looping both of the ends of the
cotton around together holding those
nicely together and in the other end is
a loop it does what it says Martin so
thread both of those two ends through
the eye of the needle pull it down a bit
but you're going to leave a gap so
you've got the loop on one end and your
two ends on the other start at the back
as before come up through the bottom
left hand corner but leave that loop
hanging at the back come down through
the top right hand hole and once you're
in the back push the needle through the
loop and it will secure it's so
beautifully to the back and you're not
wasting any thread whatsoever it's
completely secure you're not worrying
about having to then anchor in the
remaining tail and you're not having to
worry about any knots on the back you
can see here I'm stitching a row of
three half stitches and going back over
them bottom right to top left in a left
diagonal stitch to make them complete
stitches you'll see on the final third
stitch I actually come up through the
top left and down through the bottom
right it doesn't really matter as long
as the stitch is going in the same
direction to make sure they're
consistent because once you've got a
huge patch of them in the same color if
the patterns larger it will catch the
light and it will be a little bit
noticeable if you've chopped and changed
throughout the pattern again just to
finish off push the needle through a
couple of the back stitches and trim it
off and it's nicely secured and you can
see on this purple one that you've
probably used the least thread and it's
the neatest on the back it's the
smoothest on the back so definitely loop
method to start
cross-stitching would be the one that I
recommend if possible and there you can
see the finished three different ways of
starting to cross stitch on the 14 can
ADA next I'm going to show you quickly
how to use an embroidery hoop so place
the smaller hoop on the on the base of
your table or whatever you're using put
your fabric on top and then the slightly
larger outside hoop on top of that push
it down make sure you've got enough room
by turning the normally gold screw at
the top and then slowly tighten it up
once it's in position and very gently
ease out pull out some of the excess
fabric just make sure that it's nice and
taut and it's got the same tension
across the whole thing so it'll be much
easier to stitch on once you're
satisfied that it's in the right
position turn the screw as much as you
can without being too aggressive and
make sure it's all securely in place
some people like to stitch on the top of
the hoop like I'm doing here but equally
some people turn the hoop the other way
around and stitch using it a bit more
like a bowl shape either way is
absolutely fine and it just helps really
holding onto the hoop so you're making
sure no grime or dirt or anything from
your hands or at least limiting it is
getting onto the fabric so here this is
how to stitch on even weave fabric this
is 25 count even weave fabric and again
we're using a size 24 needle we're using
this beautiful color 995 DMC 995 thread
which I think will show up nicely
against this blush-pink and coming up in
the bottom left hand corner now with
even weave we're stitching two over two
which means we're using two strands of
thread in the needle and we're stitching
over two strands within the fabric so
coming up in the bottom left hand corner
and going down in the top right hand
corner but it's not the next hole along
its the one after that so in between the
bottom left and the top right there are
actually two very tiny strands of the
fabric in between those two coming up in
the top left and down in the bottom
right again as we did before on the AIDA
you'll see that these stitches are ever
so slightly larger than the ones on the
14 count Eider because 14 count Eider is
the equivalent in terms of
stitch size as 28 count even we've said
the 25 count even weave the stitches
that are produced on there it's a little
bit more like a 12 count or 13 count a
de type size some people absolutely love
even weave fabric and won't stitch on
anything else personally I think 14
count EDA is the easiest type of fabric
to start stitching on for beginners but
really is just personal preference some
people switch between the two types and
some people will always stick with one
and never divert from that I have to say
that the overall finished effect when
cross stitching on evenly fabric is way
more delicate its finer and I think it
has more of an old-fashioned vintage
feel to it and on this one I'm using the
deck the halls' gingerbread man magnetic
needle minder thank you so much for
watching guys I hope you've enjoyed this
video don't forget to click subscribe
below and also give the video a thumbs
up and I'll see you next time bye